As you can see,
Hi everyone. This is an interview and we
are here with Dr. Kinner. We are going
to have an interview about him
and I hope uh you enjoy this interview.
So who are you Drake?
I um
I was converted from atheism a long long
time ago, many decades ago um through an
experience with the Holy Spirit and um
my PhD from Duke University is in New
Testament in Christian origins
and I've written about 40 books about
20,000 pages and I'm married to Dr.
Medin Masunga Kenir who's from Congo and
Central Africa.
Okay. Uh so
I'm going to share with you uh one uh
book of him. So this is his Bible. H the
New Testament part is from him. The Old
Testament part is from Sean Welton.
And I was going to make some questions
to to Craig and we are going to talk
about it.
And also I have this commentary
uh and the Bible was made uh by the
commentary. So h I'm going to start uh
making some questions. I'm glad you are
here and you share your testimony.
Yeah.
And the and the the background
commentary also is in Spanish. Uh Kasa
Batista
published it in Spanish.
Yes, the first edition is in Spanish. Uh
we need the second edition.
It's it's actually been revised. I think
they they already have the second
edition, but I don't know how long it it
takes to circulate.
Okay, I'm going to look for Okay. Uh, so
I
It's the same cover, so you wouldn't
necessarily know that it's the second
edition, but they they did revise it.
Okay. So uh the first question I have
for you is how did the idea come about
of bringing together the Old Testament
cultural background contributions
from Walton with your commentaries
of the New Testament into one study
Bible?
Yeah, even even back when I wrote the
first edition of the background
commentary, uh it came out at the end of
1993,
I I had a vision for how we needed a
study Bible. we needed it in in study
notes because there are some things that
are really clear
um in the in the Bible. And then there
are other things where you wouldn't get
it or you wouldn't get as much without
the background. Most things context will
will resolve. But there's some things
like even knowing the words
there there are things you won't get
because there were things that the
author didn't have to explain because
the author and the audience already knew
the the background. That's why it's
called background. They didn't they
didn't have to explain it. But for us as
readers 2,000 years later, getting the
background is really vital. uh or
sometimes it's value it's not sometimes
it's vital sometimes it's just valuable
but
already back then I thought okay not
everything in the background commentary
but the most important things they
should be provided in study notes to
help people understand
um the point of some of the things that
are mentioned
and so um that had always been my vision
and then
Um, one day I forget I I just remember I
was talking with Katya at Zanderan, uh,
one of the editors at Zanderan.
And it just happened that
she was, um, she knew about a study
Bible Zanderan was going to produce. So,
she put me in touch with the right
people at Zanderan.
H boy, I forget. It was just a
providential meeting. So, it was just
right in time. And
yeah, so I agreed to do it. John Walton
and I were already friends. And
so we each stayed in our place. I did
the New Testament notes and he did the
Old Testament notes and that's how it
happened.
Okay, that's fine. I for I forgot to say
that the question was from Louis. He's
not here but because he's working but uh
here we have a second question that also
is from him
and that question is how long did the
process take and what were some of the
biggest challenges you face while
putting together?
My part was easy in one sense in that I
was able to abbreviate material from the
background commentary.
Um, and the publisher was so gracious,
you know, for a fee, but the publisher
of the background commentary allowed us
to take material from that. Obviously,
for study notes,
you know, you don't have as much room as
in the commentary. So, it had to be
condensed, but that part was easy. And
while I was doing that, I was also
working on the second edition of the
background commentary. May as well do
them both at the same time. U because I
had a lot of newer information to be
able to improve on the on the background
commentary,
but I was also going through a hard time
mentally. And I think part of it was
I was used to providing footnotes that
documented all my information like in
more technical commentaries and so like
uh I'm just repeating what I already
I've already done and that was harder on
me mentally. Um for some reason I I like
to do the in-depth scholarly work which
isn't what everybody needs. you know,
it's scholars need it and and some some
pastors may want the in-depth work, but
for ordinary readers, you don't need
everything there. So, that was harder.
And then there was something it was a
health a health issue that I went
through about the same time
because my wife and I were speaking
about ethnic reconciliation
in
uh in franophhone Africa in a country
that had just gone through war and while
we were there we spoke to 1700 pastors
that was wonderful but the antimmalaria
of prophylaxis that they put me on, the
doctor put me on actually
was counterindicated for certain nervous
conditions, but we didn't know that. And
so my wife had nightmares, but I ended
up just
like almost going berserk. I was having
panic attacks. I didn't know what a
panic attack was. So
eventually we figured it out. I was off
the medicine and onto some medicine that
helped to balance me out from from the
the nervous condition. But that had
nothing to do with the study Bible. But
that was one of the things I went
through while writing it.
Yes. But that's important actually if we
think about Paul and all what happened
to him that also is shown in in the
Bible. So I think that uh that
experience from you
actually
is important too.
Um,
so this is interesting and well uh the
next question to sorry it actually led
me to um or or or played into another
book I was writing the mind of the
spirit. I I'm not sure if it's in it
might be in Spanish. I know it's in
Portuguese. A lot of my books are in
Portuguese but that
I I think it is. I think it is.
May maybe
might might be um a number have been
translated into Spanish. But mind of the
spirit was really helpful to me because
um
and also what I was going through was
helpful to me to be sensitive and how I
wrote mind of the spirit in terms of
um
learning to depend on the spirit, the
mind of Christ and the renewing of the
mind and all those things that that Paul
talks about.
Okay. So the next question is about uh
more precisely the gospels.
So
in your work helps uh modern readers
recover the cultural world of the New
Testament. Thinking specifically about
the gospels, what are uh some common
ways people might uh misread the gospels
if they don't take that uh ground
background into account. Uh you
mentioned about uh shown uh something.
Yeah, I mean there are all sorts of
things. There's some things where where
it just helps us some to get to know
more about it. like there are historical
records about Pilate and about Herod and
so forth. Those things um just help us
to get a better picture of what was
going on so we know more about them. But
then there are places where the
background makes a total difference. Uh,
one of them I believe is the well this
one's in Paul but in 1 Corinthians 11 uh
2-16 the issue of of women wearing head
coverings in church um the background
makes a a big difference there. It was a
it was a sign of sexual modesty the same
with uh greeting one another with a holy
kiss. I was in one culture where the
women did wear head coverings in that
culture in church and so uh they were
used to that but then greeting one
another with kisses that was different
that was not part of their culture. So
um
in in in explaining the background of
that where it was a it was just a a
friendly greeting. It was just a light
kiss normally on the lips. Uh for a
superior it might be on their hand but
usually relative or or close friend it
might be a light kiss on the lips
nothing passionate. Um that was a
different kind of use of kisses. So
things like that the background makes a
big difference makes a big difference in
like a book like revelation like how we
approach revelation
um or or books like revelation uh how we
would understand them but say say the
gospel of John that we mentioned take
for example the six water pots set aside
for purification in John chapter 2 and
verse 6
what's what's that ceremony
And
why is it so significant that John has
to mention that they were set aside
specifically for purification
and it fits into a pattern in John's
gospel about uh water or purity
something being um superior to the
traditional rituals
uh and often because of the Holy Spirit
like John the Baptist says I baptize you
with water, he'll baptize you with the
Holy Spirit. Um, six water pots set
aside for purification. It says they're
they're stone water pots. Why stone?
Because in this period and for a century
or two before this,
they used stone for for many kinds of
pots because stone was considered
impervious to ritual impurity.
[laughter]
I didn't know that.
Yeah. Other kinds of containers. This is
not a this is not a water pot, but other
kinds of containers, you know, if if
something fell into it and died, you had
to break it. Another kind of pot. But if
it fell into a stone water pot,
stone was impervious. It couldn't it
couldn't contract ritual impurity. So,
you didn't have to break as many pots if
they're made of stone. And then another
issue regarding water in this case again
in John chapter 7 where Jesus says in
verses 7 and 38 37 and 38 if anyone
thirsts let them come to me let them
drink whoever believes in me as the
scripture has said from his belly shall
flow rivers of living water. What
scripture is he talking about? Well, on
the last day of the Feast of
Tabernacles, and we know from John 7:2
it was the Feast of Tabernacles, and
from John 7:37, it's the last day of
that festival. On the last day of the
festival of tabernacles,
ancient sources tell us that there were
a couple scripture readings on that day.
One was from Ezekiel 47 where rivers of
living water would go forth from the
temple in Jerusalem. And the other was
from the one passage in the prophets
that actually mentions the feast of
tabernacles. That was Zechariah 14 where
rivers of living water go forth from
Jerusalem. And so with those scriptures
in mind, Jesus says, "Rivers of living
water will go forth." And uh from from
from the belly,
the in early Jewish sources, Jerusalem
and more particularly
um the temple were considered the navl
of the earth by Jewish sources. Greeks
thought it was Delelfi.
Rome apparently thought it was Rome. But
for Jewish people, it was Jerusalem and
specifically the temple. So the rivers
of living water going forth. But what
Jesus is saying at that point is
if anyone's thirsty, come to me. I am
the source of living waters. Let the one
who who wills come to me and drink of
the water of the river of life.
And
yeah, we have all sorts of passages like
that where the where the background just
puts a new light. Now, now, not all of
John's audience even would have known
that one because that was that's based
on Jerusalem centered sources and John
is probably writing to people probably
in Asia Minor. Um
but
uh
the Jerusalem Jerusalem who'd settled in
Asia Minor over the past decade or two
um the temple probably John was writing
like 20 25 years after the temple was
destroyed. But the people who had
immigrated from Judea and settled there,
they knew it. uh people who had once
Jewish people who had once years earlier
been pilgrims to to Jerusalem for the
festivals, they knew it. So there a lot
of things like that that are really um
they they shed light on.
That's interesting. I didn't know about
the the stone uh thing.
Another one is is in Luke 15 where
the prodigal son comes home and his
father runs to him. It was considered
undignified for an older man to run.
But this father doesn't care about his
dignity so much as he cares about his
beloved son has come. Oh,
that's amazing.
Yeah, there's so many so many other
examples we could give of things that
we're often unfamiliar with,
but
they they shed light on how we
understand the gospels and the rest of
the New Testament and the rest of the
Bible.
So, uh we can move to the question
number four. Erh
well uh I'm going to ask about uh look
and act. Erh so
erh we see themes uh like reversal uh
inclusion of outsiders and strong social
dynamics. How does understanding of the
first century uh context help us uh read
these themes uh more accurately?
Erh maybe you could give h some examples
uh from ax for example erh uh you wrote
a lot about uh axe and I'm
[laughter] h this information is
valuable I think from you
yeah um yeah there's so much we could
say about Luke Acts and
yeah yeah I have written a lot about
acts
But in terms of the theme of reversal,
now that was a theme in Jewish teaching
about the time of the end when God would
exalt the lowly and so on. Of course,
it's already in the Old Testament and um
it continued in Jewish thinking about
the time of the end,
but the theme of inclusion of outsiders
was kind of contradictory to that in
Jewish thinking because it was like
we God's people have been oppressed by
outsiders, but we are going to be
exalted.
But it wasn't so much about bringing
outsiders in. There were there were
Jewish people who were interested in
that, but that was not a primary theme
in Jewish thinking in this period. There
were some places where it was more than
others. Like the people who wrote the
Dead Sea Scrolls, they were like, "No,
we we don't want Gentiles."
But then there were the people like um
some some Jewish people who lived
outside of the Holy Land and even later
rabbis they they tended to be more
welcoming towards Gentiles. So there
were there were a range of of positions.
But in terms of
uh [sighs]
welcoming of outsiders,
that was something where even even the
Jerusalem church initially had some
problems with that. God had to get their
attention um by various leadings of the
of the Holy Spirit to make them cross
those cultural barriers. So in Luke's
gospel, we see
people criticizing Jesus for eating with
tax collectors and sinners. So before I
go on from that point, let me just say a
few things about tax collectors there.
I'm not sure how tax collectors are in
Argentina, but in the US, some people
don't like them.
They are not. [laughter]
We don't like them.
But but never complain about them again
when you hear about ancient Roman tax
collectors or or those who worked for
them. Uh or or those who worked in the
in the case of Galilee, they would be
working for Herod Antipas, the governor
of Galilee. But what they did,
they could search anything. They could
go into a house, search anything. They
could search
uh maybe you have it on your clothes,
you know.
And they were so notorious
that in Egypt, and this sounds like a
joke, but it's really true.
There were sometimes when villages heard
that a tax collector was coming, the
entire village would skip town and go
start a village somewhere else to get
away from the tax collectors.
Wow. [laughter]
Yeah.
And the kids too. Uh they yeah they
everybody left the village and started
somewhere else. Uh in terms of what they
could search yes they could search
anybody except a Roman lady.
Yes. But I was thinking if they were
looking for money also in the kids.
Yep. They they well I don't know how
often they did that but they were
allowed to do it.
Yeah. It could become rather abusive.
So tax collectors who were considered as
like these are
you know these are people who
collaborate with Rome or they
collaborate with the governor who
collaborates with Rome uh or you know
their customs agents which you might
think are not so bad but when you charge
one to 2% customs
every village or town you have to pass
through that accumulates the price goes
up and up. So
um tax collectors and sinners,
the religious people were like, "How can
you hang out with these people? How can
you eat with these people?" To back then
to eat with somebody was to establish a
covenant relationship with them.
So for example, there's there's one
Greek story where two warriors were
getting ready, one was on the side of
the Greeks, one was on the side of the
Trojans. They were getting ready to
fight each other where one of them said
to the other, "I'm so and so, son of so
and so." And the other one said, "You're
son of who? Hey, my dad had your dad
over for a banquet one time." And the
other was like, "Well, we can't fight
each other. There's a covenant
relationship between our families." So,
they had to go off and fight somebody
else. But but the point is you don't eat
with people that are considered, you
know, you don't want to be friends with
them.
But in the book of Acts, who's
complaining that Peter eats with
outsiders, namely with Gentiles?
It's the Jerusalem church. So it's it's
not an issue that's just a Jewish issue.
It's a religious people issue uh that we
we look down on people who
um fellowship with people that we
disapprove of sometimes. So
you have different groups of the
marginalized in in Luke's gospel
and you have Jesus touching people or
allowing people to touch him who were
ritually impure. And so that means that
in the eyes of others, it made Jesus
ritually impure to let them do that at
least temporarily.
But Jesus, he came to save us. He
identified with us in our brokenness.
And in the book of Acts, the main group
of outsiders was Gentiles. Now today we
wouldn't say Gentiles represent the a
minority group within the church but um
but we have other other groups we might
think about because sometimes
a group that's on the margins
may be young people in some churches.
They may be the future trend of where
the church is going to be a generation
from now. And so we need to um anyway so
uh there's the theme of reversal,
there's the theme of uh the marginalized
and uh the third thing you asked about
oh strong social dynamics. I mean there
are so many things there that we could
we could look into. uh say for example
in Luke 14 where you've got invitations
to a banquet and
back then people would signify that they
were coming. They they they already
responded to say that they were coming.
So when the host at the banquet sends
out notice for them to come, it's
because they've already said they were
going to come and now what he's saying
is the food's ready. And then one after
another makes an excuse. And these have
to be coordinated. These excuses are so
bad that it's like they're directly
insulting the host. So to say, I married
a wife and I can't come. Uh back when
you said you were coming, you already
knew you were going to marry a wife. And
person says, I bought a field. I need to
go look at it. Who's going to buy buy a
field and not look at it beforehand? So,
I mean, they're giving such bad excuses.
These are deliberate insults to the
honor of the host. And
the host can only recoup his honor by
getting other people to come to the
banquet. So,
again, we could we could give lots of
examples, but those are just a a handful
um on the specific issues that you
mentioned.
Yes. I was thinking about uh the women
uh for example
uh for example we have uh uh Mary the
the young virgin and I found uh
something special uh because uh we see
uh Zachchariah
and we can compare both I I read that in
your Bible actually
because it's a table and
um I also uh want to ask you about the
women because they they they appear
everywhere.
Yeah.
And that was not common.
Yes. Yeah. It's even even as as much as
women appear in Mark was not common as
much as they appear in Luke was
definitely not common. And you have
things like uh in Luke 10:38-42,
you have Mary sitting at Jesus' feet.
What does that mean? I mean, he's
teaching. She's sitting at his feet.
That was the expected posture of a
disciple. We see that in Mishna Abot 11.
That's a
Jewish reference. But it's also the only
other time that Luke uses that phrase,
sitting at somebody's feet is when Paul
says in Acts 22:3, "I sat at the feet of
Galeio."
The posture of a disciple. Mary's taken
the posture of a disciple. And that was
something women barely ever were
privileged to do. Um, we have I mean I
could say never but we have some like
sort of minor exceptions but basically
women were not well we can say this for
sure women were not trained as
disciples. So for Mary to be welcome in
that role was a significant statement
about about women and this theme
continues in the book of acts. Uh also
there's a sub theme regarding women
about widows and and Jesus uh care for
uh well Jesus in the church's care for
for widows
uh like raising the widow of Naan's son
or raising uh Tabitha is caring for
widows in Acts nine. Um yeah just a lot
of [snorts] a lot of things. Um, and
women are there on the day of Pentecost
at the, you know, they're part of the
co-ed prayer meetings uh in Acts 1:14
and and and yeah, what you said about
Mary, the contrast with Zechariah, I
mean, you would expect Zechariah to be
the the big hero of that section, but
ancient sources often would compare two
different characters.
And so you have various levels of
comparison, various points of
comparison. So to each of them in Luke
chapter 1, Gabriel the angel appears.
And when Gabriel appears, they're both
shocked, which is not surprising for me,
too. [laughter]
Yes. Surprising at all.
In both cases, the angel says, "Don't be
scared." which, you know, makes sense.
Uh, but it goes on down, you know,
uh, there's going to be a son. This is
going to be a miraculous birth. He'll be
great. Here's what his name will be.
Here's what his mission will be. And
then they ask a question or in
Zechariah's case, give an objection and
they get an answer. So various points
where they're compared and some of them
are almost the same but on some of them
obviously
Mary gets the greater calling. Her son
isn't just to introduce the Messiah. Her
son is is the Messiah, the son of God.
But normally what you would expect is,
hey, this guy's a priest. He's in
Jerusalem. He's in the temple, you know,
great great place, great role. He's he's
old and seniority was highly valued in
that culture. He's male which was also
more highly valued. But Mary, who's
apparently a teenager, virgins, well,
usually women got married very young
back then. Uh
many of them could get married as young
as puberty.
And so she's probably a teenager.
So, she's she's young, she's female,
she's in Nazareth, which is like, who's
heard of Nazareth except for in the
Gospels? Um, I mean, Nathaniel had heard
of it, but he said, "Can any good thing
come out of Nazareth?" John 146. So, um,
and yet given their response,
Zachchariah is muted for his unbelief
temporarily. Mary is praised for her
faith.
And that's that just sets the tone right
up front at the beginning gospel.
I was
No, no, continue. Continue.
No, just another example of the marginal
and the social dynamics you asked about.
Yes. H you mentioned about widows and I
read something in Substack uh a couple
of days ago and widows
uh are more important than than just
always I I read something about the
first Timothy and uh a parallel maybe.
Oh yeah. Oh yeah. There's some
interesting stuff on first Timothy. No
but but not my substack, right?
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, [laughter]
no. You don't have substack. You don't
have subst. [clears throat]
Exactly. I don't have Substack. Somebody
somebody created the Substack in my
name. It's not mine. But anyway, yeah.
First Timothy 5. Um, the false teachers
in First Timothy seem to be targeting
widows because
women had less education.
They were a lot more vulnerable because
of that to to false teaching than the
men were. But hey, who better to target
than than widows if you know if you know
that the women are going to be more
vulnerable? Who better to target than
the widows? Not just because they don't
have husbands, but because if you're
going to start a church back then, where
did the church meet in homes? In which
group of women most often owned their
own homes? Was widows.
So, it's not surprising that the false
teachers were targeting women. And that
makes that makes important sense when
you look at uh 1 Timothy chapter 2. And
um I don't know this might be a little
controversial um more controversial at
least than the women wearing head
coverings but in 1 Timothy chapter 2
where Paul says I'm I'm not allowing a
woman to teach or or to usurp authority
or well there's different ways to
translate it different uh I won't get
into the translation issues because
we're just dealing with background here
but um it's interesting that this would
come up. You know, Timothy had worked
with Paul before. If this was Paul's
practice everywhere, we wouldn't expect
him to have to tell Timothy that. And
like in Romans chapter 16, he mentions
all sorts of women who worked with him.
You know, he's got friends, women who
are doing ministry like you're doing
now. He's got
friends who are doing this stuff. But
when it comes to 1 Timothy 2, he says,
"No, a woman's not allowed to do this."
What does he mean? Why is he saying that
here? And I think it's interesting that
this appears in the one set of letters
where we specifically know that false
teachers were targeting women. So 2
Timothy 3:es 6 and 7 mentions the false
teachers targeting
he says weakwilled women.
Uh now there's a whole lot I mean that
passage requires a whole lot more.
There's so much more discussion. We
could go on for hours just on that
passage uh and and different
perspectives on it. But I do think that
bears some you know mention why why Paul
highlights that issue there.
Okay. So we can move to the next
question. Uh for those teaching or
sharing the gospel today, how can we use
a cultural background responsively
without going beyond what the text
actually supports?
Yeah.
There are a lot of things that happened
in antiquity
that we can talk about that aren't
really relevant to the text and
sometimes people want to force them to
be relevant to the text like so people
will sometimes read things into texts uh
especially when they're talking about
especially when they've only studied
like one stream of ancient background.
So like if they've only studied Greek
background,
they sometimes read that into the text
when the Jewish background is closer. Or
if they've only studied Jewish
background, sometimes, especially when
you get beyond the gospels uh and the
first half of Acts,
um sometimes the Greek background or the
Roman background is more pertinent.
And also
[sighs]
and then sometimes people introduce
other kind they'll talk about gnostic
background when we don't have clear
evidence for full-fledged gnosticism
until the second century. It's it's not
really very relevant for the first
century. Um comment, you know, if you
got commentaries from like 20 years ago
or 30 years ago, a lot of them highlight
that as background.
it's not really such good background
and scholars periodically change their
minds on things uh as new information
comes out and there's fads and fashions
in scholarship like there is anywhere
else. So, I've tried to
focus on the things that are more
certain,
although there were reasons why I wanted
to do a second edition rather than the
first because I learned so much between
the two. Um,
and so, especially as I'm limiting the
information I'm including for the for
the study Bible, I was trying to trying
to focus on the most relevant
information.
At the same time,
[sighs]
there are things that may fit
um
suggestions for ancient background that
might fit, but they're not really
Yeah, they're not really the most
relevant thing. You have to look at what
is relevant to helping you understand
the text. And there's some things again
that are valuable
but aren't vital.
It's valuable to know stuff about
Pilate. Oh well, that's why Pilate acts
like this. It's valuable to know how
bloodthirsty Herod was when he thought
anybody challenged his kingdom. He
killed some of his own children when he
thought that they were challenges to his
kingdom.
So, it's not surprising he killed the
male children of Bethlehem in chapter
two. So things like that are valuable to
know, but then some of the things we've
talked about are more vital to know
where just we would miss a nuance
without the background. And then there's
some things where some cultures need
certain kinds of background more than
others. Like in northern Nigeria when I
taught there,
they had a better understanding of how
head coverings worked than do a lot of
cultures unfamiliar with head coverings.
And cultures that practice
uh kisses as friendly greetings are are
more familiar with that than are some
other cultures.
My um my wife's culture is more familiar
with, you know, kisses as greetings with
her on the cheek in her culture.
Yes. Here in Argentina is normal, too.
Yeah, that's good.
Yes. So there's some places where you
know there are things in the background
commentary or the study Bible you might
say why even include that in a note we
know that but then
there may be other things you say give
us more background on this that I didn't
even think of needing because I mean I
tried to think of different cultures
when I was doing it but uh so
and people from the Mediterranean world
there are things that intuitively and
and even from my wife's world in Africa.
uh and given a lot of the Mediterranean
influence in Latin America, uh there are
things that people may take for granted
may be obvious,
but then uh some of the archaeological
discoveries and like the stone water
pots or
when it talks about uh people
actually when it talks about um
Gentiles
being immersed in water.
That was an act of conversion in early
Judaism. Not everybody used it. I mean,
circumcision obviously always was used
for for male converts to Judaism, but
often at least there also was a
ceremonial washing when a person
converted to Judaism. And so when John
the Baptist
is baptizing Jewish people in the River
Jordan with a once-for-all kind of
turning from one way of life to another
way of life and saying, "Don't think to
say to yourselves, we have Abraham as
our ancestor. God is able to raise up
from these stones children for Abraham."
That was um
he's basically saying
Jewish people, Gentiles, you all have to
come to God the same way. God has no
grandchildren. Can't just depend on our
ancestry.
Uh and in the same context where he
calls
some of his hearers offspring of vipers,
uh I I first wrote in this a few decades
ago. Uh, I think it's more widely known
now, but there was an ancient view that
the way people were born, and this not
the way people were born, the way vipers
were born, they would chew their way
through their mother's guts, killing
their mother in the process.
And so calling people offspring of
vipers is like saying
you have the you're the moral equivalent
of parent murderers. M
so
things like that are things where
knowing the background sheds a lot of
light.
Yes, I was thinking uh something
h
about the last question but I have a
question about tongues. H maybe you
could tell us about the tongues because
some people think that this is not
available today [laughter]
and that kind of stuff.
This is not a question. This is a
theology question. [laughter]
Yes, it's a question.
Okay, that's fine.
in Acts 2:17 and 18 or actually 16-18
because Peter is explaining what's
happened with them speaking in tongues
and he says this fulfills what the
prophet Joel said in the last days which
is actually a paraphrase of Joel. Joel
says afterward, but Peter knows the
context is talking about the last days
um before just before the sun turns dark
and the moon and and you know the great
and terrible day of the Lord uh and God
restoring his people in Joel chapter 3
of the English translation. So in
yeah Peter says in the last days God
says I'll pour out my spirit on all
flesh. Your sons and daughters will
prophesy. Your young men will see
visions. Your old men will dream dreams.
And then Peter adds in another line
that's not there in Joel. But you were
allowed to paraphrase give an explan
explanatory paraphrase. This is just
emphasizing the point that's there in
Joel. And they'll prophesy. This was
prophetic empowerment. empowerment to
speak for God. Now, if it was the last
days at that point when
this was happening on that day of
Pentecost in Acts chapter 2, it's
certainly the last days now. In fact, if
anything, we might say, you can't really
do this in English, but you might say
it's laster days now.
So, um, clearly those things are for
today. 1 Corinthians chapter 13 actually
says
when these things will pass away. He he
says, you know, we know in part, we
prophesy in part. Um
that that covers teaching, that covers
prophecy.
These things are partial, but there's
coming a time when it'll be complete. We
won't need anything partial anymore.
We'll know even as we are known. We'll
see them face to face.
And so, but what that also implies is
these gifts continue until that time.
And and I can give some background
related to it too. I mean, Jeremiah 31
um with the fullness of the new
covenant, they won't any any longer
teach their neighbor um saying know the
Lord because each of them from the least
of them to the greatest of them will
know the Lord. And obviously Joel's
background and even going back to
numbers chapter 11 where people are
prophesying
u 70 elders are prophesying and then
they stop but then eldad and midad are
prophesying in the camp and somebody
runs to Moses and says
um they're prophesying in the camp and
Joshua says my lord make them stop and
and in numbers 11:29 Moses says
don't be jealous for my sake I wish that
all God's people were prophets And so
when Joel says, "Your sons and daughters
will prophesy," that's a fulfillment of
of Moses's wish and it's an expectation
for the for the end time uh for the era
in which we're living that we are the
people of the spirit and therefore these
these gifts continue. We also need
discernment. That's another gift that
should go along with them. But yeah,
thank God for for the spirit and and the
gifts.
Okay. I don't know. I Yes, I see Louis.
[laughter]
I don't know if he if he wants
No, I I just came out of the the
phrases. So, I just I just u I've been
hearing everything you've been saying.
So, I have a I have a final question,
but uh it has to do more with your
institution. Uh so for you can let
everybody knows uh what you do for the
Spanish speaking community. I don't know
if you are involved in that. Uh Ashland
uh uh Ashbury Latino remember there's a
there's also a uh an offering of masters
in ministry and masters of arts in uh
from from where you work.
Yes. Yeah. And that's very important.
Now I don't do anything directly there
because
I don't speak Spanish. I mean there are
a few words uh [clears throat]
um
you know and so on but uh
deo uh you know things like that but
[laughter]
but I don't know enough to teach in
Spanish. So but
your books your books are well received
in Spanish. Uh I'm hoping that I'm not
afraid of the rapture or something. You
remember one of your books? [laughter]
Yes.
Uh cuz cuz that's a that's a big and now
with the things happening in Iran, you
know, everybody's saying this the end. I
said, well, if you're a
dispensationalist, you don't think this
this is the end. There has to be a seven
sevenyear gap. So I guess um BO has
another last question. I'll let her I'll
let her make it.
Yes. Yes. My last question is okay.
Where's question number six? [laughter]
Where's question number six? Okay.
Question number six. Was there any
cultural insight in Luke? In Luke or in
the Gospels uh that personally surprised
you or changed how uh you understand
or understood a passage?
Yeah, plenty. Um, but let me I talked
about Luke chapter 1, the opening
narrative with Zechariah and Mary. So,
let me go back to the verses immediately
before that, Luke 1:1-4.
And
some of the wording that Luke uses was
standard wording used in historical
prefaces in the ancient world. And most
of it is translated, you know, we're
used to the way most of it's translated,
but then
um there's one one word that in a lot of
English translations is investigated,
but actually it was used by historians
in their prefaces to mean something even
more than investigated. It means a
thorough personal acquaintance.
Well, that would make sense when you get
to Acts 16:10
and periodically through the rest of the
book of Acts where Luke says we and he
travels with Paul including he spends up
to two years in Judea. So, he would have
access to eyewitness sources and all
sorts of all sorts of great information.
But I mean that's that's one example.
Obviously there there lots of possible
examples we could give. Actually let me
give another one from Luke chapter 2 if
it's all right if I'm not taking too
long.
Yes. Yes. Yes. Okay. [clears throat]
Of course.
This this uh for for uh thinking about
this for Christmas although uh Luke
chapter 2 probably happened at a
different time than when we celebrate.
It's Navididad in Spanish.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, so different from when we celebrate
Christmas, but this was um the emperor
Augustus
sends everybody back to where they're
from for a tax census. We talked about
tax collectors before. So, Augustus
looks like he's the big mover and shaker
in this in this narrative.
Joseph and Mary go back to Bethlehem
and there it doesn't say she she was
giving birth right when they got there
like in the movies. Uh but I understand
that's the way you should do a movie.
That's that's appropriate. But um but
while she was there she gave birth and
it doesn't say in Greek in the inn. I'm
not sure if in is the translation used
in Spanish translations, but uh in
English it makes it look like it's a
hotel. Uh actually, it's a room. Uh it's
different than the word Luke uses later
for in in Luke chapter 10. So, but it's
in a manger. It's an enamel feeding
trough. And then
uh the angel declares to the shepherds
how
um this is the the
good news good news on earth peace
towards towards humanity. Um you have
another series of contrasts in this
narrative. Shepherds were considered low
life. They were consider they were
despised in most of the Roman world
especially by elites and
Augustus
was worshiped in imperial temples.
And the the priests of Augustus who led
the worship, they were chosen from among
the elite
and they would hail Augustus the emperor
as the savior of the world. They they
hailed him as the supreme king
and on his birthday um they would they
would have special celebrations
throughout the Roman Empire.
But when Jesus was born,
his birth was celebrated by shepherds,
by the lowly. And when Jesus was born,
it was heavenly choirs rather than
earthly choirs who praised him. And they
praised him as the savior of the world
and the bringer of peace. Augustus was
hailed as the bringer of peace for the
Roman Empire. that Jesus came to bring
two true peace between God and humanity.
And so
God chose to send his son first of all
among the lowly, not in the palace, but
in an animal feeding trough.
And we find God's presence especially
among the lowly.
So, so that could be the um the how can
I say because in Luke we see that the
the mag guys they go to to to the king.
They're looking for the high class
people.
Jesus is king of kings and lord of
lords. He's greater than the emperor.
But the magi uh in Matthew 2,
they worked well they could work for the
Persian king, make the Persian king look
good. But when they come to worship the
King of the Jews, that's unexpected. You
know, for Matthew's first audience,
probably Jewish audience, first time
they hear this, they're going to be
like, "What? The magi?" Because magi
were Persian astrologers.
And what we know from the Old Testament,
these are not going to be the good guys.
But in this case,
they're the ones who came to worship the
king of the Jews.
Herod who kills the male children. Who
in the Old Testament killed male
children?
Pharaoh.
And so you have the king,
the king of the Jews who acts like a
pagan king. And you have these pagans
who act like God's people. And this fits
a motif that runs all the way through
Matthew's gospel up and up through until
you get to the great commission in
Matthew chapter 28 where it talks about
making disciples of all the nations.
And Matthew recounts these incidents
to remind his uh especially Jewish um
Jewish followers of Jesus audience to
remind them
that God's mission is to all peoples.
Amen. Amen. Um anything else or are we
okay? We're almost up to the hour.
Yes. Uh I would like to say that I
watched a video like a year ago uh from
you Craig and I was encouraged by that
video. Uh it was a 5 minute uh video
only but you said uh you you could make
a difference and actually my channel is
one year. [laughter]
[gasps]
It has only one year and I started this
channel and and I I I
am I'm happy with that. So
thanks. Thank you. Gracias.
Much gracias to you. Yeah.
Well, thank you very much. It's been a
great pleasure. Uh, actually your Bible,
uh, Betto already has it, but uh, I'm
I'm waiting for it. It's going to come
on the 6th of April, which is my
daughter's birthday. So, there you go.
See?
So, you can your daughter.
Yeah. Well, it's it's in Spanish. My
daughter doesn't My daughter's was All
my children were born here. So So, so,
so they speak this weird type of
Spanish. Look at Boo. She's holding her
her Bible very proudly. [laughter]
Well, the Bible says that we should do
Oh, anyway. So, um we're going to do an
unboxing and then we're going to um uh
we're going to uh put up um this
interview. Oh, there there you go. See,
V also has your book. I also have it,
but I'm not I'm not I'm not at home. I'm
at work.
Yes, I have I have like two more books.
[laughter]
HPA
is one of of them.
Um then I have many in kind of so in
kindo. So
and I have the and I have the
hermeneutics of the spirit book and
because I'm going to teach between the
history and the spirit.
Mhm.
But look inside how is it called in
English. Look inside in the first page.
How is it called in English?
Yeah. Some some of them
some of them
they changed the
the title meanings. Yeah.
Um so I just want to ask you about the
hermeneutics of the spirit that would be
like a post-graduate level book of
hermeneutics. Yes. More
you think so? So yeah, when I when I
when I start students with hermeneutics,
I start them with the basics like um
context,
background,
um different genres or literary types.
Um so I start with the basics like um
probably F and Stewart, how to read the
Bible for all its [clears throat]
probably in Spanish, I would imagine.
Yes, it is.
Yeah.
Yeah. [clears throat] So usually I start
on that that kind of level.
Okay.
So yeah, this would be more advanced.
Okay. Thank you.
That is going to tell you.
Yes. The title is between history and
spirit.
That's a different book.
Yeah.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
That's a book in the book of Acts.
Yeah.
I don't have [clears throat] that one,
so I need I need to bring it.
It's arguing for the historical
reliability of acts and then talking
work of the spirit in acts.
Yes.
Okay. Thank you. Then I we don't want to
take more time. Maybe if once we close
maybe you can stay one minute and so I I
want to show you something. Uh but uh
I'll let Bto close because Betto I I
think she's done a great job. Uh in the
beginning she was very nervous but but
she but she has now she speaks like a
native. Now ch. Yes.
Amen.
Yes. Can you close please?
It looks
Oh. Uh and this is the we always uh
I hope this interview
Yes. Uh I hope
this is
okay. And
Mhm. [clears throat]
You're cutting off. That's why.
Oh no.
At the end. That's the good thing. At
the end. You didn't cut off during the
interview. At the end.
Okay. Okay. Okay. Now.
Yeah. Now. Do it now.
Okay. Uh, thanks Craig for being here. I
hope this encourage the church and the
audience uh for being a better Christian
and know more about Jesus Christ. Thanks
for being here.
Thank you for having me. Thank you very
much.
Thank you.
[music]
Heat.